Finding Aid for the Miriam Matthews photograph collection, 1781-1989 LSC.1889
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Daily Life in Black Los Angeles and California., 1885-1980.
  - Artists and Entertainers.
    - W.C. Handy, blues composer and musician. (Box 21, Folder 15)
      Includes portrait and photograph of Pace & Handey Music Co., Inc. in New York.
    - Leon Rene Sr. and Jr., composers of rhythm and blues and rock and roll songs., 1930s-1950s. (Box 21, Folder 16)
      Photograph of father and son.
    - Le Chevalier de Saint-George, 18th century classical composer of African descent. (Box 21, Folder 17)
      Includes drawing of Le Chevalier de Saint-George.
    - Samuel Coleridge-Taylor, English composer of African descent., early 20th century. (Box 21, Folder 18)
      Portrait of Coleridge-Taylor at the piano.
    - Leading African American Composers and Arrangers. (Box 21, Folder 19)
      Group photograph includes William Grant Still, H. Lawrence Freeman, W.C. Handy, Rosamund Johnson, Will Vodery, Charles Cooke, Noble Sissle.
    - Portraits of African American Composers, Conductors, and Arrangers. (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Includes portrait (negative) of William Dawson, Nathaniel Dett, Walter Howard Loving, and Harry T. Burleigh.
    - Choirs, Piano Academies, and Music Schools. (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Includes photographs of groups from Professor Wilkins' Piano Academy recitals (1917 and 1923?); article on Gilbert Allen Singers in Silhouette Magazine; music and dance teacher Lauretta Butler, Professor Wendell Talbert and wife Florence Cole, Midland Jubilee Singers (1911); flier for Freita Shaw's Ethiopian Chorus in Concert; group portrait "The Only Original University Singers of New Orleans"; Williams Jubilee Singers touring Europe; and another Jubilee Singers group (unidentified).
    - Southeast Symphony Association. (Box 22, Folder 3)
      Photograph of group working at home of Jessie Terry.
    - Early Motion Picture Actresses. (Box 22, Folder 4)
      Includes portrait of Madame Sul-Te-Wan, Hattie McDaniel, Dorothy Dandridge, Louise Beavers, and Lillian Randolph.
    - Bill "Bojangles" Robinson, tap dancer and actor. (Box 22, Folder 5)
      Includes portrait of Robinson dancing, and photograph of his house designed by Paul Williams.
    - Clarence Muse, actor, screenwriter, director, and composer. (Box 22, Folder 6)
      Includes photograph of Muse playing an accordion from a New Year's card, and a flyer for "Grand Studio Ball & Movie Classic" produced and directed by Clarence Muse, at Warner Brothers Studio.
    - Rochester (Edward Anderson) and Jack Benny entertain U.S. troops., 1942. (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Motion Picture Actors (male)., 1930s-1980s. (Box 22, Folder 8)
      Includes photographs of Canada Lee, Noble Johnson, Paul Robeson, James Lowe, Rex Ingram, and Raymond St. Jacques.
    - Photographs of Noble Johnson, loaned to California African American Museum. (Box 22, Folder 9)
      Includes Johnson, actor and president of Lincoln Motion Picture Co., with directors from the black production company (c. 1921) and Noble Johnson with unidentified man behind camera.
    - Black Motion Picture Production Companies. (Box 22, Folder 10)
      Includes negative of portrait of actor and director Frank Silvera, photograph of four members of board of directors for Lincoln Motion Picture Co., photograph of former site of Lincoln Theater, print of Amended Articles of Incorporation Lincoln Motion Picture Co. (1921), photograph of black supporters of "Hollywood Productions - Negro Movie Co." in 1939, photograph of group of black actors (including Muse, Beavers, Norman, Ingram, and Blount), and screen shots from "Purlie Victorious" with Ruby Dee and Ossie Davis
    - Black Actors in White Studios. (Box 22, Folder 11)
      Includes photograph of W.E.B. DuBois visiting child actor Ernest Morrison "Sunshine Sammy" at Hal Roach Studios with prominent women of black Los Angeles, and photograph of scene from "Pardon Us" with Laurel and Hardy in blackface with Freita Shaw acting. She also directed her Ethiopian chorus for the soundtrack of this film. Also included are photographs of cowboys for an unidentified film.
    - Black Entertainers, photographed in the 1980s. (Box 22, Folder 12)
      Includes publicity stills of television show "Say What?" and James Bond film "A View to A Kill." Promotional photographs of Bill Cosby and Patti La Belle, television show "The Jeffersons," television show "The Cosby Show," singer and actress Melba Moore, R&B group "Lakeside Appears With Lou," actor Dorian Harewood, R&B and soul singer Richard "Dimples" Fields, guitarist and songwriter Ray Parker Jr., actress Danielle Spencer, jazz singer Al Jarreau, actor Hal Williams, and white country music singer Charlie Daniels.
    - Jazz and Popular Music vocalists. (Box 22, Folder 13)
      Includes photographs of a young Johnny Mathis, Nat King Cole with Raymond Burr, Sammy Davis Jr., and Lou Rawls.
    - Jazz Musicians, individual portraits. (Box 22, Folder 14)
      Includes portraits of pianist Ahmad Jamal, pianist Jelly Roll Morton, saxophonist Paul Howard, pianist Billy Taylor, pianist Ray Charles, and saxophonist Reb Spikes.
    - Jazz musicians, groups. (Box 22, Folder 15)
      Photographs of Reb Spikes with the Majors and Minors Orchestra (1925 and 1928), Sammy Franklin's Orchestra. Two men and two women cutting cake labeled by Miriam Matthews "Carpentier, Musicians."
    - Female classical and operatic soloists., 1870s-1950s. (Box 22, Folder 16)
      Portraits of soprano Hattie Hopkins-Moore, contralto Carol Brice with her brother and accompanist Jonathan Brice, singer in Dusseldorf, Germany Annis Hackley, coloratura soprano Mattawilda Hobbs, opera soprano Sissieretta Jones, contralto Emma Louise Hyers in scene from "Out of Bondage", soprano Anna Madah Hyers in scene from "Out of Bondage," Marian Anderson, and classical pianist Pauline Powell Burns.
    - Jane Phillips, author and musician., 1963?. (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Male lyric and operatic vocalists. (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Includes portraits of Marion Hayes, Roland Hayes
    - Nightclub Scenes and Performers. (Box 23, Folder 2)
      Includes photographs of Sammie Franklin's Orchestra and Joe Morris' Plantation Club.
    - Vaudeville Performers, Variety Entertainment, and Theatrical Actors., 1900-1933. (Box 23, Folder 3)
      Includes photographs of Clayton "Peg-Leg" Bates, Maurine and Ivan Harold Browning (1921), a 4th of July Quartet, Ethel Waters in the musical venue "As Thousands Cheer", Charles Gilpin in various dramatic roles, Noble Sissle and Eubie Blake in an early Vitaphone movie short (c. 1930), and an unidentified actress from Virginia Stephens' estate.
    - Bert Williams, vaudeville actor and comedian., early 1900s. (Box 23, Folder 4)
      Includes portrait of Williams and Williams in a group photograph with the Frogs, a theatrical fraternal organization for African Americans when they were excluded from white groups.
    - Portrait of African American Architect, Cloud. (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Paul Revere Williams, Los Angeles-based architect, portraits. (Box 23, Folder 6)
      Portraits of Paul Williams, including photographs, and a photographic copy of an oil painting.
    - Paul Revere Williams and family. (Box 23, Folder 7)
      Photographs of Williams with Charles Matthews and Frederick Roberts at wedding reception of eldest daughter, Williams with his wife at the Wilfandel Club, Williams with his daughters, and Chester Williams, Paul's brother.
    - Awards and Accolades of Paul Williams. (Box 23, Folder 8)
      Photographic copies
    - Buildings designed by Paul Williams as Head or Associate architect. (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - 1939-1940 World's Fair, Marching Band and unidentified portraits from mid-20th century. (Box 23, Folder 10)
      Marching band directed by Kernan D. McFarlin
    - League of Allied Arts., 1939-1964. (Box 23, Folder 11)
      Established by Juanita Miller and Dorothy Vena Johnson when they pooled resources to present a play written by Langston Hughes in Los Angeles when there was no space for an African American to do so. Images include a portrait of Johnson, and photographs of groups presenting exhibitions, 1963-1964
    - Portraits and works of black male artists in Los Angeles. (Box 23, Folder 12)
      Includes works and photographs of David Bradford, William Pajaud, Herman Bailey, William E. Smith, Richmond Barthe (negatives), John Biggers, West Gale, Marion Epting, and Ron Adams. Also includes work of Mexican artist Chinas.
    - Portraits of Charles Alston and Hale Woodruff, artists behind Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Murals. (Box 23, Folder 13)
      For photographs of the murals and their dedication, see Box 1, Folder 14-17.
    - Betye and Alison Saar, both artists. (Box 23, Folder 14)
      Includes individual portrait of Betye (mother), with Alison (daughter)
    - Grafton Brown, lithographer and painter., c. 1883. (Box 23, Folder 15)
      Includes portraits of Brown, photographs of four of his paintings, and a photocopy of a biography taken from "The Kahn Collection of Nineteenth-Century Paintings by Artists in California" by Marjorie Arkelian from the Oakland Museum (1975).
    - Sculpture by Sargent Johnson. (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Works of Beulah Woodard, Sculptor (1 of 2)., c. 1930-1950. (Box 24, Folder 2)
      First African American artist to show her work at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. She also founded the Los Angeles Negro Art Association in 1937. She specialized in African subjects.
    - Works of Beulah Woodard, Sculptor (2 of 2)., c. 1930-1950. (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Portraits of Beulah Woodard with her sculpture., c. 1930-1950. (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Alice T. Gafford, painter. (Box 24, Folder 5)
      Includes portraits of Alice Taylor Gafford and her mother Alice Taylor, several photographs of some of Gafford's paintings, and a photograph of Gafford as a nurse with the Red Cross in Alaska before she became a painter.
  - Civil Rights Leaders and Organizations.
    - Male Leaders from the Classic Civil Rights Movement. (Box 27, Folder 11)
      Includes photographs of Martin Luther King Jr., Clayton Russell, Byron Rumford, Roy Wilkins, a prayer pilgrimage to Washington, and a civil rights event at Memorial Coliseum in which King Jr. and Dick Van Dyke spoke, along with civil rights ministers.
    - W.E.B. Du Bois, scholar, civil rights activist, author., 1913-1919. (Box 27, Folder 12)
      Includes negative of portrait of Du Bois and negative photograph of his visit to Los Angeles.
    - Medgar Evers, memorial in Los Angeles. (Box 27, Folder 13)
      Includes photographs of event at Holman Methodist Church and a march to South Park.
    - Voter registration and mobilization. (Box 27, Folder 14)
      Includes photographs of the Community Improvement Association's voter registration drive, and a covered wagon bus to register voters.
    - Housing restriction and residential covenants. (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Check List of State Anti-Discrimination and Anti-Bias Laws., 1948. (Box 27, Folder 16)
      Photographic copy of chart compiled by the American Jewish Congress. Includes laws for Alabama, Arizona, Arkansas, and California.
    - Tarea Hall Pittman, civil rights activist., c. 1923. (Box 27, Folder 17)
      Includes an early photograph of Pittman taken in Bakersfield
    - Marnessa Tackett, civil rights leader and former Director of Southern Christian Leadership Conference, Western division. (Box 27, Folder 18)
      Includes two portraits of Tackett.
    - Loren Miller, civil rights attorney and judge. (Box 27, Folder 19)
      Includes individual portraits, a photograph with Byron Rumford and unidentified man.
    - Picketing, civil rights demonstrations. (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - NAACP, Los Angeles Chapter. (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Includes photographs of a planning meeting for the National Convention to be held in Los Angeles that summer, Human Rights Banquet honoring Philip Murray, late president of the C.I.O., a portrait of Roy Wilkins, executive secretary of the NAACP, an executive board meeting in 1923, group photo of some founders and some former presidents.
    - NAACP, Junior Branch, Los Angeles., 1925. (Box 28, Folder 3)
      Group photograph of members in 1925, and a photographic copy of the official charter of the junior division of the Los Angeles branch.
    - NAACP President Walter White visits Los Angeles., 1937. (Box 28, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs of Walter White, met at the railroad station in Los Angeles by prominent black citizens including Dr. John Somerville, Frederick Roberts, Rev. Samuel Beane, and Rev. Ernest Lightner.
  - Churches and Ministers.
    - First A.M.E. Church, Old Church on Azusa Street., c. 1890s. (Box 17, Folder 11)
      One of earliest sites of the First African Methodist Episcopal Church in Los Angeles, before moving to Eighth and Towne in the early twentieth century. In 1906, this building became the site for interracial Azusa Street Revival, leading to a global spread of Pentecostalism.
    - First A.M.E Church building on 8th and Towne., 1901-1972. (Box 17, Folder 12)
      In 1901, Rev. Jarrett E. Edwards, then pastor of the First A.M.E. Church, commissioned a new home for his congregation. Includes photographs of the exterior of the church building, which was instrumental in the twentieth- century civil rights movements, as well as the site of 8th and Towne after it was destroyed by fire in 1972.
    - First A.M.E. Church groups and individuals at 8th and Towne., 1901-1972. (Box 17, Folder 13)
      Includes photographs of Hamel Hartford Brookins, pastor and civil rights activist at First A.M.E. from 1965 to 1978; Prof. Elmer Bartlett presented a loving cup for his contributions to the NAACP; groups photographs of the congregation and important churchwomen.
    - Dedication of Historical Plaque at 8th and Towne., 1973. (Box 17, Folder 14)
      Includes photographs of church members, the plaque, and architect Paul Revere Williams making a speech.
    - First A.M.E. Church choir., 1909- 1930s. (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of organist and first choir director Professor Elmer Bartlett; church choir in front of building (including local saxophonist James Smith); church choir inside the sanctuary; church choir performing at the Hollywood Bowl.
    - Conferences held at the First A.M. E. Church, Los Angeles., 1923-1960. (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Includes the Golden State Council and Juveniles in 1914; the 56th Annual Session of the California Conference of the A.M.E. Church in 1923; a group photo of A.M.E. Church bishops in 1925 (location unknown); the General Conference of the A.M.E. Church in 1960
    - "Churches, Negro in Los Angeles" from Binder compiled by Miriam Matthews., c. 1965. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Includes photographs of Crouch Temple, Chester Baptist Day School, People's Independent Church of Christ, New Bethel A.M.E. Church, Old Bethel A.M.E Church, Old Avalon Christian Church, Hamilton M.E. Church, Phillip's Temple C.M.E. Church, Second Baptist Church, Church of the Advent (Episcopal), Holman Methodist Church, Wesley Chapel, First A.M.E. Church on Azusa Street. Many photographed by Harry Adams in the 1960s.
    - Second Baptist Church, Los Angeles., 1920s-1960s. (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs of Rev. Raymond Henderson (pastor 1941-1963) and wife, Dr. Thomas Lee Griffith (pastor 1921-1940) and family, the church building, A.C. Bilbrew speaking or receiving an award, and Mary McLeod Bethune speaking.
    - People's Independent Church, Los Angeles., 1915-1953. (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Includes negative of Rev. N. P. Greggs, and photograph of Rev. Clayton D. Russell and his wife Gwendolyn Diggs. Also includes framed photographs of the church building before it was enlarged, the groundbreaking and laying of cornerstone of the church (many congregants in full Masonic or other lodge regalia), the choir, the trustees, the deaconesses, and the church board. Many photographs from the Shackleford family.
    - St. Phillip's Episcopal Church, Los Angeles., c. 1912- 1950. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Includes photographs of Rector Rev. William Cleghorn, church school students, an early church guild of women, picnic in Eastlake Park, and vestry board.
    - Wesley Chapel, M.E. Church., undated. (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Photographs of church building (exterior), one taken by Dr. A.C. Garrott, located on 8th and San Julian Sts.
    - Westminster Presbyterian Church, Los Angeles., c. 1910. (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Includes photographs of congregation and a Sunday School class.
    - St. Matthias Episcopal Church. (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of the interior of the church and a Sunday school class.
    - Hamilton M.E. Church. (Box 18, Folder 10)
      Includes photograph and negative of church congregation in front of the building with Rev. Beane.
    - Church of Christian Fellowship, Women's Day (negative)., 1954. (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Los Angeles Plaza Church., 1822. (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - William Seymour, leader of Azusa Street Revival., 1906-1909. (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Seventh-Day Adventist Camp Meeting., c. 1900. (Box 18, Folder 14)
      Photograph taken by Dr. A.C. Garrott
    - Wedding of African American couple in an unidentified church., undated. (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - African American Churches in Pasadena. (Box 18, Folder 16)
      Includes St. Barnabas Episcopal Mission and Church, an unidentified church group from 1907 (possibly Scott Methodist Church), and a negative of another Episcopal church, possibly St. Cyprian's.
    - Rev. James Lodge, San Jose., c. 1865. (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Includes photograph of James Lodge and wife, and individual portrait with Bible.
    - Rt. Rev. T.M.D. Ward, A.M.E. Church presiding elder in California (negative)., c. 1849. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Rev. Charles Satchell and First Colored Baptist Church, San Francisco., founded 1856. (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Church became Third Baptist Church because First and Second Baptist were two white congregations. Includes negative of Charles Satchell. Also includes photograph of Third Baptist Church and Mt. Olivet Baptist Church in Marysville, also pastored by Rev. Satchell.
    - Rev. J. B. Sanderson, first appointed minister of the First A.M.E. Church, Oakland., 1874. (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Includes portrait of Rev. Sanderson and portrait of his granddaughter Kate Sanderson DeGrasse.
    - Churches in Fresno., 1916/1917. (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Includes photograph of Second Baptist Church and Bethel A.M.E Church, both African American churches in Fresno. Taken from the East Bay Directory.
    - Churches in Sacramento., c. 1915. (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Includes photograph of St. Andrew's A.M.E Church from East Bay Directory, and part of choir for Shiloh Baptist Church with Rev. McPherson.
    - Grace Episcopal Church, San Francisco. (Box 19, Folder 7)
      Description on back of photo: "This White Episcopal Church plant was sold to an A.M.E. Negro Church"
    - Episcopal Minister. Mobile, Alabama. (Box 19, Folder 8)
      Unidentified negative.
  - Social clubs, Greek societies, Community Organizations.
    - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority Binder compiled by Miriam Matthews. (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Delta Sigma Theta sorority, groups outside of Los Angeles. (Box 24, Folder 7)
      Includes photographs of Berkeley campus chapter (1921), 12th National Convention in Chicago (1933), Open House in San Diego, Alpha Chapter at Howard University
    - Delta Sigma Theta, Los Angeles chapters. (Box 24, Folder 8)
      Includes photograph of Nu Sigma graduate chapter, Western Regional directors (1972), Reception at home of Lillian Tyler (1932), members of chapter at Iva Washington's home in Manhattan Beach, Los Angeles regional conference, National Convention (1935), charter members (1929), Santa Monica chapter. Also includes Nona Moffett, 1946 president of Omega Sigma graduate chapter of Bay Area.
    - Kappa Alpha Psi fraternity, UCLA., 1924. (Box 24, Folder 9)
      Photograph of charter members from UCLA
    - Boule, Sigma Pi Phi fraternity. (Box 25, Folder 1)
      First Greek letter fraternity founded by African American men. Includes photographs of Washington D.C. chapter, Los Angeles chapter, 26th Biennial Grand Boule (1962), at Moulin Rouge in Los Angeles, wives of LA Boule members in 1945.
    - Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity. (Box 25, Folder 2)
      Includes photographs from the Alpha Phi Alpha souvenir program, USC Alpha Delta chapter (1921), Pan-Pacific Convention (negative, 1936), Alpha Delta Chapter in 1936 (negative)
    - Rho Psi Phi Medical Sorority, Los Angeles., c. 1924. (Box 25, Folder 3)
      Established by Emily Brown Portwig in 1924. Includes photographs of sorority house with members in front, and a photograph of the house from a magazine.
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha sorority., 1920s-1960s. (Box 25, Folder 4)
      Includes group photographs of AKA women, a Regional Conference in 1931, a group of AKAs with Marian Anderson,
    - Pi Sigma Alpha, National Honorary Political Science fraternity USC. (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Zeta Phi Beta sorority, Beta Sigma Zeta chapter, Tampa, Florida., 1950. (Box 25, Folder 6)
      Group photograph
    - First Annual Formal Dance of the Faben Phi Fraternity., 1912. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Photograph of dance at Blanchard Hall, April 18, 1912.
    - Prominent Los Angeles club women and civil rights activists., 1890-1949. (Box 25, Folder 8)
      Includes photographs of women who founded several clubs in black Los Angeles: Kathryn J. Baskins Barr who organized an employment agency that later became the Los Angeles Urban League; Betty Hill who organized the Women's Political Study Club and was a founding member of the LA chapter of the NAACP; Margaret Scott, one of founders of the Sojourner Truth Club in 1904 and later served as president; and Mary McLeod Bethune (not from Los Angeles) who was involved in the National Association Colored Women, National Council of Negro Women, National Youth Administration.
    - Boys Club. (Box 25, Folder 9)
      Includes photographic copy of invitation to dedication of Southern Area Boys Club (1957)
    - Black Masons in Los Angeles. (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Includes photographs of conventions, lodges, temples, and past Masters, Grand Masters and other officers.
    - Desert of California Ancient Egyptian Arabic Order Nobles Mystic Shrine Inc. (aka Shriners). (Box 25, Folder 11)
      Includes Gilbert Lindsay, the first black City Council member, Rocky Washington, and Egyptian Temple Drill Team (1945).
    - Knights of Pythias, California. (Box 25, Folder 12)
      Includes photographs of Knights of Pythias in California and Los Angeles.
    - Elks Temple, Los Angeles. (Box 25, Folder 13)
      Photograph of temple building on Central Avenue.
    - Unidentified Lodges. (Box 25, Folder 14)
      Includes photographs of black men and unidentified lodge events.
    - Y.M.C.A., Los Angeles., 1909-1967. (Box 25, Folder 15)
      Includes photographs of the first building on the 800 block of San Pedro Street, the building on 9th and Hemlock with Thomas Greene, the 28th Street branch, the Los Angeles Citizens Band.
    - Y.W.C.A, Los Angeles. (Box 25, Folder 16)
      Includes photographs of building on 12th Street Branch, the later Woodlawn Branch, Mattie Scott Nelson, executive secretary of the 12th Street Branch, and
    - Asilomar Conference, YMCA/YWCA. (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Includes two group photographs from the conference in different years, multiracial attendees.
    - Stovall Foundation. (Box 26, Folder 2)